hello and welcome
it's active inference guest stream
number 51.1 on July 28 2023
we are here with Tomaso Salvatore and we
will be having a presentation and a
discussion on the recent work causal
inference via predictive coding so
thanks so much for joining for those who
are watching live feel free to write
questions in the live chat and off to
you thank you
thank you very much Daniel for inviting
me uh always been a big fan of the
channel and I've been watching a lot of
videos I'm
I'm quite excited to be here and uh and
be the one speaking this time
so I'm going to talk about these recent
preprint that I that I put out which has
been the work of the last couple of
months
and the it's a collaboration with the
with lookup in Ketty I'm in makarak
barami Legend Thomas lukasiavich
and it's basically a joint work between
verses which is the company I work for
the University of Oxford and uhuvian
so
during this talk
I will
this basically the outline of the talk I
will start talking about what predictive
coding is
and the given interactions of what it is
a brief historical introduction why you
think is uh is important to study
creative coding even for example for the
from the machine learning perspective
I will then provide a
small intro to what causal inference is
and and once we have all those
informations together I will then
discuss uh why I wrote this paper what
was basically the research question that
inspired me and the and the other
collaborators
and present the main results
which are how to perform
inference so intervention and
counterfactual inference
and how to learn the causal structures
from a given data set using predictive
coding and then I will of course
conclude with some
small summary and some discussion on
why I believe this work can be in fact
impactful and some future directions
so what is creative coding
creative coding is in general famous for
being a neuroscience inspired learning
method so what theory of how information
processing in the in the brain works
and
very formally speaking the tier of
creative coding can be described as
basically having a hierarchical
structure of neurons in the brain and
and you have two different families of
neurons in the brain
the first family is the is the one in
charging of sending prediction
information so neurons in a specific
level of the hierarchy send informations
and and predict the activity of the of
the level below
and the second family of neuron is that
of error neurons and the arrow neurons
they send prediction error information
up the hierarchy so one level predicts
the the activity of the level below
this activity has some this prediction
as some mismatch which would actually
going on in the level below
and information about the prediction
error gets sent up the arrow key
however predictive coding is
was actually not burned as a
neuroscience as a theory from from the
neurosciences
but it was actually initially developed
as a method for Signal processing and
compression back in the 50s so the the
work of Oliver Elias which are actually
contemporary of uh clothes Shannon of
Shannon
they realized that once we have a
predictor a model that works kind of
that is well in predicting data
sending messages about the error in
those predictions is actually much
cheaper than sending the entire message
every time
and this is how pretty coding was born
so as a
as a signal processing and compression
mechanism in information Theory back in
the 50s
it was actually in the 80s uh that that
it became that exactly the same model
was used in uh
in neuroscience
and uh so with the work from Mumford or
other works for example explain how the
how the rating of process information so
we get prediction signals from the
outside world and we need to to compress
this representation and uh and have this
internal representation in our neurons
and the method is very similar if not
equivalent to the one that was used that
was developed by by Elias and Oliver in
the 50s
maybe what's the biggest Paradigm Shift
happen in 1999
thanks to the work of around Ballard
in which they they are they introduced
this concept that I mentioned earlier
about hierarchical structures in the
brain where prediction information is
top down and the error information is
bottom up
and something that they did that wasn't
done before is that they
they explain and develop this theory
about not only in France but only but
also about how Learning Works in the
brain so it's also a theory of how our
synapses get updated
and the last big breakthrough that I'm
going to talk about in this brief
historical introduction is from 2003 but
is uh then he kept going in the in the
years after uh thanks to car freeston in
which basically he he took the theory of
Robin Ballard and he developed a
he extended it and generalized it to to
the theory of generative models so
basically the main claim that that
carfiston did is that creative coding is
an Evidence maximization scheme of a of
a specific kind of generative model
which I'm going through to to introduce
later as well
so to make a a brief summary in the the
first two
uh kinds of creative Corner that I
described so signal processing and
compression and the information
processing in the retina and in the
brain in general they are inference
methods
and the biggest
change the biggest Revolution that we
had in 1999 so let's say in the 21st
century is the operative coding was seen
as a learning algorithm so we can first
compress information and then update all
the synapses or all the latent variables
that we have in our generative model to
to improve our generative model itself
so let's let's give some uh definitions
that are a little bit more formal
so operative coding can be seen as a
hierarchical gaussian generative model
so here is a very simple figure in which
we have this hierarchical structure
which can be as deep as we want
and Signal prediction signals goes from
go from one latent variable XM to the
following one and it gets transformed
every time via function GN
or GI
this is a generative model as I said and
what's the marginal probability of this
generative model well it's simply the
probability of the last
can you see my my cursor yes right yeah
it's perfect so it's the genetic model
of the last vertex is the Sorry probably
distribution of the last vertex times
the probability distribution of every
other vertex conditioned on the activity
of the vertex before or the on the
latent variable before
I I already said that it's a gaussian
generative model which means that those
probabilities they are in gaussian form
and every
endos function function G in general and
uh especially since for example in
Rambler paper and in all the papers that
came afterwards also because of the deep
learning Revolution those functions are
simply linear Maps or
non-linear maps with activation
functions or nonlinear maps with
activation function and an additive bias
so we can we can give a formal
definition of creative coding and we can
say operative coding is an inversion
scheme for such a generative model where
its model evidence is maximized by
minimizing a quantity that is called the
variation of free energy
in general the goal of every generative
model is to maximize model evidence but
this quantity is always intractable and
we have some
techniques that allow us to to
approximate the solution and the one
that we that we use in Creative coding
instead of minimizing aberration of free
energy which is a which is a lower bound
of the model evidence in this work and
actually in a lot in in a lot of other
ones so it's the standard way of doing
it this minimization is performed the
ingredient descent
um and yes perform we agreed in descent
and there are actually other methods
such as expectation maximization which
is often equivalent
or you can use some other message
passing algorithms such as belief
propagation for example
and going a little bit back in time so
forgetting a little bit about the
statistical generative models
if we can see creative coding
as a I mean I said already a couple of
times as a hierarchical model
with the neural activities so with
neurons latent variables that represent
neural activities the sender signal down
the hierarchy
and with error nodes or error neurons
the sender signal up the hierarchy so
this and the error information back
what's the variation of free energy of
this class operated coding models it's
simply the sum
of the mean square error of all the
error neurons
so is the is the sum of the of the error
of the total error squared
and this representation is going to be
useful in uh in the later slides and in
how I'm going to explain how to use
creative coding to model causal
inference for example
I think predictive coding is important
and it's not is a nice algorithm to
study
well first of all as I said earlier it
optimizes the correct objective which is
the model evidence or marginal
likelihood
and
then it does so by optimizing a lower
bound which is called the variation of
free energy as I said and the virtual
finish is interesting because it can be
written as a sum of two different terms
which are and each of those terms of
optimizing it as uh as important impacts
for example in in machine learning tasks
or in general in learning tasks
so one of those term forces memorization
so in the second term basically tells
forces the model to fit a specific data
set
and the first term
forces the model to minimize the
complexity and as we know for example
for the from the of outcomes razor
Theory if we have two different models
that perform similarly on a specific
training set the one that we have to get
and the one that is expected to
generalize uh the most is the less
complex one
so updating a generative model via
operational free energy allows us to
basically
converge to the optimal uh outcome razor
model which is which both memorizes a
data set but it's also able to
generalize very well on unseen unseen
data points
a second reason of why operative coding
is important is that it's actually not a
doesn't have to be defined on
hierarchical structure but it can be
modeled on more complex and flexible
architectures such as directed graphical
model with any shape or generalized even
more to networks with a lot of cycles
that resemble brain region and the end
result in the underlying reason
is that you're not learning and
predicting with a forward pass and then
back propagating the error but you're
minimizing an energy function
and this allows basically every kind of
hierarchy to be
uh
allows to go behind direct keys and
allow to to learn cycles and this is
actually quite important because the
brain is full of Cycles as we have some
some information from some recent papers
uh that are managed to map completely
the the brain of some animals such as
fruit fly
the brain is full of Cycles so it makes
sense to to drain our machine learning
models or our
our models in general with an algorithm
that allows us to drain using
cyclic structures
the third reason why operative coding is
interesting is that it has been formally
proven that it is more robust than
standard neural network starting with
black propagation so if you have a
neural network and you want to perform
classification tasks
you creative coding is more robust
and this is a
interesting in tasks such as online
learning training on small data sets or
continuous learning tasks and the theory
basically comes from the fact that
imperative coding has been moved to
approximate implicit gradient descent
which is a different version of the
explicit gradient descent which is the
standard green descent used in the
in every single model basically
and it's a variation that is more robust
I think okay I did a quite a long intran
operative coding I think I'm now moving
to the second topic which is causal
inference
and the what's causal inference causal
inference is a theory it's a very
general theory that has been formalized
the most by Judy apparel he's definitely
the the most important person in the
field of causal in France he wrote some
very nice books for example the book of
Y is highly recommended if you want to
learn more about this topic
and it basically tackles the following
problem
so let's assume we have a joint
probability distribution which is
associated with a Bayesian Network this
is going to be a little bit the running
example through to all the paper
especially when you're not with Asian
networks of this shape
it was based on networks the the
variables inside they can represent
different quantities so for example our
visual network with this shape can
represent the
the quantities on the right so social
economical Studio statue of an
individual its education level its
intelligence and its income level
something the classical statistics is
very good at and is it's uh while uh
most used application is to model
observations or correlations a
correlation basically answer the
question what is the if we observe
another variable C
so for example in this case what is
what's the income level the expected
income level of an individual if I
observe this education level
and of course if that person has a
has a higher degree of education for
example a master or PhD I'm expecting
General that person to have a higher
income level
and this is a correlation
however sometimes there are things that
are very hard to observe but they play a
huge role in determining those
quantities
so for example it could be that the
income level is much much more
defined by the intelligence of a
specific person
and and maybe that the intelligence or
if a person is intelligent is also most
likely to have a higher education level
but still the the real reason why the
per the income is I is because of the of
the IQ
and this can be this cannot be Studies
by simply correlations and has to be
studied by by a more advanced technique
which is called an intervention
an Intervention basically answers the
question is what is D if we change C to
a specific value
so for example we can we can take a an
individual and check his income level
and then change its education level so
intervene on this world
and change its education level without
touching his intelligence and see how
much is a its income changes
for example if the income changes a lot
it means that the the intelligence
doesn't play a big role in this but the
education level does if the income level
doesn't change much it means that maybe
there's a hidden variable in this case
the intelligence that determines the
income level of a person
the third quantity important causal
inference is that of counterfactuals so
for example a counterfactual answers the
question what would the be and we change
C to a different value in the past
so for example we can see that the
difference between interventions and
counterfactuals is that interventions
act in the future so I'm interviewing in
the world now to observe a change in the
future well counterfactual allow us to
go back in time and change a variable
back in time and see how that change
would have influenced the world we live
in now
and those are defined by judapple as the
three levels of causal inference
correlation is the first level
intervention is the second level in
counterfactual is the third level
other interventions I'm going to Define
them more formally now now that I gave
an intuitive definition and I'm I'm
using this notation here which is the
same actually throughout all the
presentation so X is always going to be
a latent variable s i is always going to
be a data point or an observation
and VI is always going to be a Vertex so
every time you see VI we're only
interested in the structure of the graph
for example
so let's assume we have a Bayesian model
which has the same structure as the
as the Bayesian model we we saw in the
previous slide
given that X3 is equal to S3 this is the
observation we make statistics allows us
to compute the probability or the
expectation
of X4 which is the latent variable
related to this vertex
given that X3 is equal to S3
foreign
intervention we need a new kind of
notation which is called the do
operation
so in this case
X4 we want to compute the probability of
X4 given the fact that we intervene in
the word and change X3 West 3.
and how do we do this to perform an
intervention Judo Pearl tells us that we
have to
to have an intermediate step before
Computing a correlation is at first we
have to remove all to remove all the
incoming edges to V3
so we have to study not this Bayesian
Network but this second one
and then at this point we are allowed to
compute a correlation as we as we
normally do
and this is an intervention
a counterfactual is a generalization of
this that as I said lived in the past
and they're Computing using structural
causal models
a structure causal model is a tuple
which is a conceptually similar to a
Bayesian Network but basically we have
this new class of variables on top which
are the unobservable variables they use
so we have the Bayesian Network that we
had before X1 X2 X3 S4
but we also have those unobservable or
variables that depend on the environment
you cannot control them you can infer
them but you
but they they are there
and
f is a set of functions that depends on
all the
basically f of x of x3 depends on X1
because we have an arrow on x2 because
you have an arrow and on the
unobservable variable that also
influences extreme
so yes intuitively you can see us you
can think of a structural causal model
as a Bayesian Network with those
unobservable variables on top and each
unobservable variable only influences
its own
its own latest variable X so for example
IU will never touch X1 as well u3 will
will only touch Q3 E1 will all influence
X1 and so forth and so on
so performing counterfactual inference
answers the following question so what
would X4 be at X3 been equal to another
variable in a pass situation you
foreign
requires three different steps so
abduction
is the
is the computation of all the background
variables so in this in this step we
want to go back in time and understand
how the environment the unobservable
environment was
in that specific Moment In Time
and we do this by fixing all the latent
variables X to some specific data that
we already have
and and Performing these uh this
inference on the used
then we're going to use the U
to keep the U that we have learned and
perform an intervention
so
a counterfacture can also be be seen as
an intervention back in time in which we
know the environment the environment
variables U1 U2 and u4 in that specific
moment
and
what's the missing step
so what would X4 be at X3 been equal to
another
another data point in that specific
situation now now we can compute a
correlation
and the correlation we do it on the path
on the on the graph in which we have
already performed an intervention using
the environment variables that we have
learned in in the abduction step
and this is a counterfactual inference
this is the last slide of the causal
inference present introduction
and is about structural learning
basically basically everything I've said
so far relies on the fact that we know
the causal dependencies among the among
the data points so we know the structure
of the graph we know which variable
influences which one
we know the arrows in general
but in practice this is actually not
always possible so we
we don't have access to the causal graph
most of the times and actually learning
the best causal graph from data is still
an open problem we are improving in this
we are getting better but
how to perform this task exactly
uh
is still an open problem
so as I said basically the goal is to
refer Council relationships from
observational data so given a data set
we want to infer the directed exactly
graph that describes the connectivity
between the system and the variables of
the data set
so for example here we have an example
that I guess we are
all familiar with thanks uh because of
the pandemic so we have those four
variables age vaccine hospitalization
and and CT
and we want to infer the causal
dependencies among those variables so
for example we want to learn directly
from data that the probability of a
person being hospitalized depends on on
its age and on the fact whether it's
vaccinated or not and so forth and so on
so this is the end of the long
introduction but uh I hope it was clear
enough and I hope that I gave like the
basics to understand the
basically the results of the paper and
now we can go to the research questions
so the research questions are the
following
first I want to see
whether creative coding can be used to
perform causal inference
so operative coding so far has only been
used to perform to compute correlations
in in Bayesian Networks
and the big question is can we go beyond
correlation and model intervention and
counterfactual in a biological plausible
way
so in uh
in a way that it's for example simple
intuitive and allow us to only play with
the neurons and not touch for example
the huge structure of the graph
and More in practice more specifically
the question becomes can we Define
operative coding based structure causal
model to perform interventions and
counterfactuals
the second question is
as I said that having a structure custom
model assumes that we know the structure
of the evasion Network
so we it assumes that we have the arrows
can we go beyond this and use creative
coding networks to learn the causal
structure of the graph
basically giving positive answers to
both those questions would allow us to
use predictive coding as an end-to-end
causal inference method which basically
takes a data set and allows us to test
interventions and counterfactual
predictions directly from this data set
so let's let's tackle the first the
first problem so causal inference
vibrative coding which is also the
section that gives the the title to the
paper basically
and here I will show how to perform
correlations operative coding which is
uh already known
um and how to perform Interventional
queries which which I think is the
is the real question of the of the paper
so here is a causal graph which is the
usual graph that we
that we had
and here is the corresponding creative
coding model so the axes are the the
latent variables and correspond to the
neurons in a in a neural network model
and The Black Arrow passing from
prediction information from one neuron
to the to the one down the hierarchy
and every vertex also has this error
neuron which passes information up the
hierarchy so the information of every
error goes to the to the value node in
the up the hierarchy and basically tells
it to to correct itself to change the
prediction
so to perform a correlation using
predictive coding what you have to do is
that you take an observation and you
simply fix the value of a specific
neuron
so if you want to compute the
probability of X4 given X3 equal to S3
we simply have to take X3 and fix it to
S3 in a way that it doesn't change
anymore and run an energy minimization
and this model
and by minimizing by updating the axis
uh via a minimization of the variation
of free energy allows the model to
converge to a solution to this question
so the probability or the expected value
of X4 given X3 equals 3.
but how do I perform an intervention now
without acting on the structure of the
graph
well this is the basically the first
idea of the paper
oh this is still how to perform a
correlation so fix S3 equal to X3 is the
first step in the algorithm and the
second one is to obtain the axis by
minimizing the variation of free energy
an intervention which in theory
corresponds in removing those those
arrows
and answers to the question the
probability of X4
by performing an intervention so do X3
equals three imperative coding can be
performed as follows
so I'm going to write the algorithm here
so first as in a correlation you fix S3
equal equal to the iFix X3 equal to the
observation that you get
then this is the important step
you have to intervene not on the graph
anymore but on the prediction error and
fix it equal to zero
having a prediction error equal to zero
basically
makes uh sends meaning meaningless
information up the hierarchy or actually
sends no information of the hierarchy
because it basically tells you that the
prediction is always correct
and the third step is to as we did
before to update the axis the
unconstrained Axis or X1 X2 X4 by
minimizing the variation of free energy
as I will show now or experimentally by
simply doing this little trick of
setting a prediction error it to be
equal to zero
is a prevents us to actually act on the
structure of the graph as a
as the theory of do calculus does and to
infer the missing uh the variables after
an intervention by simply performing
aberration of free energy minimization
what about counterfactual inference
counterfactual inference is actually
easy once we have
Define uh how to do an intervention
and this is because as we saw earlier
performing a counter factually similar
to performing an intervention in a past
situation after you have inferred the
unobservable the unobservable variables
so
as you can see in the plot I showed
earlier about the abduction action and
prediction steps the action and
prediction steps they did not have those
two arrows
they were removed pretty coding allows
allow us to keep the arrows of this uh
in the graph
and and perform counterfactuals by
simply performing an abduction step as
it was done earlier
an action step in which we simply
perform an intervention on the single
node so we fix the value node and we set
the error to zero
and run the energy minimization to
minimize the duration of free energy to
compute the prediction
so I think this is like an easy and
elegant method to perform interventions
and counterfactuals and uh
yeah so I think the the thing we have to
show now is whether it works in practice
or not and we have a couple of
experiments
and I'm going to show you now two
different experiments the first one is
merely uh proof of concept experiment
that shows that in the operative coding
is able to perform
intervention and counterfactuals
and the second one actually shows a a
simple application in how Interventional
queries can be used to improve the
performance of classification tasks on a
specific kind of operative coding
Networks which is that of a fully
connected model
let's start from the first one
so how do we do this task so given a
structural Council model
we generate training data and we use it
to learn the weights so to learn the the
functions of the structural Kaza models
and and then we generate test test data
for both Interventional and
counterfaction queries
and we show whether we are able to
converge to the correct test data using
creative coding
and
and for example here uh in those two
plots represent Interventional
intervention and counterfactual queries
of this specific graph which is the
butterfly bias graph which is a graph
that is often used in uh in testing
whether a causal inference whether
intervention and counterfactual
techniques work is as simple as that but
in the paper you can find a lot of
different graphs but in general those
two graphs those two plots show that the
method works shows a show that the the
the
mean absolute error between the the
Interventional counterfactual quantities
we we compute and the Interventional and
counterfactual quantities from the
original graph
are close to each other so the error is
quite small
the second experiment is uh is basically
an extension of an experiment I proposed
in a in an earlier paper which is the
learning on arbitrary graph topologies
that I that I wrote last year
in that paper I
basically propose those this kind of
network as a proof of concept which is a
fully connected Network which is in
general the worst neural network you can
have to perform
machine learning experiments because
given us a fixed set of neurons
basically the
you have every pair of neuron is
connected by two different synapses so
it's the most is the is the model with
the highest complexity possible in
general
the good thing is that since you have a
lot of Cycles the model is extremely
flexible in the sense that you can train
it for example on on a minced image and
on a data point and on its label but
then the way you can query it thanks to
the information going back is uh you can
query in a lot of different ways so you
can form classification tasks in which
you provide an image and you run the
energy minimization and get the label
but you can also for example perform
generation tasks in which you give the
label run the energy minimization and
get the image you can perform for
example image completion which you give
half the image and converge and and
converge let the model convert to the
second half and so forth and so on so
it's basically a model that learns the
the statistics of the data set in its
entirety without being like focused on
classification or generation in general
so this flexibility is great the
the problem is that because of this it
like every single task doesn't work well
so you can do a lot of different things
but none of them is done well
and
here I want to show how using
Interventional queries instead of
standard uh correlational queries or
conditional queries
slightly improves the results of those
classification tasks
so what are the conjective reasons of
these uh the test accuracy on
on those tasks not being so high the
first the two reasons are that the model
is distracted in correcting every single
uh every single error so basically you
present an image and you would like to
get a label but the model is actually
updating itself to also predict the
error in the images
and the second reason which is the one I
said is that the structure is is far too
complex so again from from an outcome
raisin Occam razor
argumentation
this is the worst model you can have so
every time you have a model that fits a
data set that model is going to be less
complex than this one that is going to
be preferred
but in general uh just to just to study
it
the idea is can query in this model the
interventions be used to improve the
performance of uh of those fully
connected models
well the answer is yes
so here is how I perform Interventional
queries so I present an image to the
network
I fix the error of the pixels to be
equal to zero so this error doesn't get
propagated in the network
and then I compute the label
and as you can see the accuracy improves
for example from 89 using the standard
query method of creative coding networks
to 92 which is the accuracy after
intervention and the same happens for
for fashion means
and I think that a very legit critic
that probably everyone would think when
when seeing those plots is that okay you
improve on means from 89 to 92
still sucks basically and yeah it's true
and I'm actually in the later slides I'm
going to show how to act on the
structure of this uh of this fully
connected model
will improve the results even more until
the point they reached the rich uh
performance that is not even close to
state of the art performance of course
but it's still up but isn't up to a
level that becomes basically acceptable
Kenworth investigation investigating
so yes so this is the was the part about
causal inference using creative coding
and I guess to summarize I can say that
uh the interesting part of this uh of
the results already I just showed is
that I showed operative coding is able
to perform interventions in a very easy
and intuitive way because you don't have
to act on the structure of the old graph
anymore sometimes the those function
functions are not available so forth and
so on but you simply have to
you simply have to
intervene on a single neuron studies
prediction error to zero
and perform uh an energy minimization
process
and these extended are allowed us to
Define creative coding based structural
causal models
Now we move to the second
part of the work which is about
structural structure learning
so instruction learning as I said Deals
Deals with the problem of learning the
causal structure of the model
from observational data
this is actually no problem that has
been around or decades and
and was has always been until a couple
of years ago tackled using combinatorial
search methods
the problem with those community
research methods is that they their
complexity grows double exponentially
so as soon as the data becomes
multi-dimensional and the
the Bison graph that you want to learn
grows in size
learning it it's it's incredibly slow
the new solution that came out actually
a couple of years ago in a new newspaper
from 2018
show that it's possible to actually
learn this structure not using a
combinator research method but by using
a gradient based method
and this this was basically this skilled
problem in general because now you can
you can simply
have a prior on the parameters which is
the priority purpose that I'm going to
to define a little bit better in this
slide
run gradient descent and even if you
have a model that is double triple the
size
is uh the algorithm is still incredibly
fast
and for this reason this paper is a
this is yeah I think it's kind of new
and I think already has around 600
citations or thing or things like that
and every paper that I'm seeing now
about counseling friends and learning
structure of the graph uses their method
it just changes a little bit the
they find faster or slightly better
inference methods but still they all use
the prior the this paper defined and I
do as well and we do as well
so here we will find a new quantity
which is the agency Matrix the agency
Matrix is simply a matrix that encodes
the connections of the model so it's a
binary Matrix and
in general is a binary Matrix then of
course when you do gradient based
optimization you you make it continuous
and then you have some Threshold at some
point that basically kills an edge or or
set it to one
and the M3 IJ is equal to into one if we
have if the Bayesian graph as an edge
from from vertex I to vertex J or zero
otherwise so for example this agency
Matrix here represents the connectivity
structure of this visual Network
and
basically this method
tackles to two problems that we want
about these uh about learning the
structure of the equation Network the
idea is that we start from a fully
connected model which
conceptually is uh is similar actually
is equivalent to the operative coding
Network I defined earlier which is fully
connected so you have you have a lot of
vertices and every pair of vertices is
connected by uh by two different edges
and you simply want to prune the ones
that are not not needed
so it can be seen as a as a method that
performs model reduction you start from
a big model and you want to make it
small
so what's the first ingredient to to
reduce models well is of course sparse
City
and what's the prior that everyone uses
to to make a model more sparse is the
LaPlace prior which in machine learning
is simply known as the L1 Norm
which is defined here
the solution that the this paper that I
mentioned earlier proposed is to add the
second prior on top which enforces what
what's probably the the biggest uh
characteristic of Bayesian networks the
on which you want to perform causal
inference is that you want them to be a
cyclic
and basically they showed that
acyclicity can be imposed on an agency
Matrix as a prior
and it has this the this shape here so
it's the trace of the Matrix that is the
uh the exponential of a times a
where a is the agency Matrix again and
basically this quantity here
is is equal to zero if and only if the
Bayesian Network or the
or the whatever graph you're considering
is a c click
so I'm going to use these in uh in some
experiments so those two into Force
those two priors on the
on different kinds of patient networks
and I'm trying to merge them with the
techniques we proposed earlier about
performing causal inference the
operative coding
so I'm going to present two different
experiments so one is a is a proof of
concept which is the standard
experiments showed in all the structural
learning tasks which is the inference of
the correct Bayesian Network from data
and then I'm going to to build on top of
the classification experiments I showed
earlier
and uh
and show how actually those priors allow
me allow us to improve the
classification accuracy the test
accuracy of fully connected predictive
coding models
so let's move to the first experiment
which is to infer the structure of the
graph
and all the experiments they all follow
basically the same pipeline in all the
papers in the field the first step is to
generate a vision network from random
graph
so basically normally the two random
graphs that everyone tests are Erdos
renegraphs and scale free graph
so you you generate those big graphs
that normally have 20 for the 80 80
different nodes and some edges that you
that you sample randomly
and you use this graph to generate a
data set
so you sample for example
n Big N data points and what you do is
that you take the graph that you they
have generated earlier and you throw it
away you only keep the data set
and the task you want to solve now is to
is to learn
is to have a training algorithm that
basically allows you to
to retrieve the structure of the of the
graph you have thrown away
so the way we do it here is that we are
in a fully connected creative coding
model on this data set D using both the
sparse and the SQL priors we have
defined earlier
and and see whether actually the
the graph that we converge to after
pruning away the
the entries of the agency Matrix that
are smaller than a certain threshold is
similar to that of the of the initial
graph
and there's also show that this is
actually the case so this is an example
and I show many different
parametrization and dimensions and
and things like that in the in the paper
but I think those two are the most
representative examples with an error
Nursery graph and a free scale graph
with 20 nodes
and here on the left you can see the
ground through graph which is the one
sampled
randomly
and on the right you can see the graph
the pretty difficulty model as learned
from from the data set
and as you can see they are quite
similar
it's still not still not perfect so
there are some there are some errors but
in general the structure is
they work quite well we also have some
quantitative experiments that that we
that I don't show here because they're
just huge tables with a lot of numbers
and I thought it was maybe a little bit
too much for the presentation but but
the results show that they perform
similarly to to contemporary methods
also because I have to say like most of
the quality comes from the on the acigli
prior that was introduced in in 2018.
the second class of experiments is the
our classification experiments which as
I said are the extensions of the the one
I shared earlier
and the idea is to use structure
learning to improve the classification
on the classification results on the
means and fashion means data set
starting from a fully connected graph
so what I did is that I divided the
fully connected graphing clusters of
neurons so 1B cluster is the
is the one related to the input
and all the small then we have some a
specific number of hidden clusters
and then we have the label cluster which
is the
the class the cluster of neurons that
are supposed to give me the the label
predictions
and I've trained them using for using
the first time the sparse prior only so
the idea is what if I if I prune the
connections I don't need from a from a
model
and and learn as parser model
does this work well the answer is no it
doesn't work and the reason and the
reason why is that you at the end the
graph that you converge with is actually
the generate so basically the model
learns to predict the label based on the
label itself so it discards all the
information from the input
and only keeps the label and as you can
see here the label y predicts itself or
in other experiments when you change the
parameters you have that y predicts at
zero that preex X1 the predicts y again
so what's the what's the solution to to
this problem well the solution to this
problem is that we have to
to converge to an acyclic graph
and so we have to add something that
prevents a cyclicity and what is that
one is of course the one I already
proposed and then I I show a second
technique
so the first one uses the SQL prior
defined earlier
and the second one is a is a novel
technique that actually makes use of
negative examples
so a negative a negative example in this
case is simply uh the a data point in
which you have an image but the label is
wrong
so here for example you have an image of
a seven but the label that I'm giving
the model is a two
and
and the idea is very simple in is has
been used in a lot of uh Works already
so every time the models is a positive
example it has to increase to to
minimize the variation of free energy
and every time it has a it is a negative
example it has to increase it
so let me move on the error this
quantity to be minimized
foreign
with a lot of experiments and a lot of
uh of experimentations we saw that the
two techniques
basically first lead to the to the same
results and second lead to the same
graph as well
so here are the
here are the new results some means and
fashion means using the two techniques
that I that I just proposed
and and now we move to some which are
still not uh great but definitely more
reasonable test accuracies so here we
have a test error of 3.17 for mins and a
test error of 13.98 for fashion means
and actually those can be those results
can be much improved by learning the
structure of the graph from minced
and then fixing the structure of the
graph and and do some form of fine
tuning so if you fine tune the model on
the correct hierarchical structure at
some point you reach the test accuracy
which is the one you would expect from a
hierarchical model but those ones are
simply the one the fully connected model
as naturally converged to
so so for example from a test error of
18.32
of the fully connected model train on
fashion means by simply performing
correlations or conditional queries
which is a standard way of querying
operative coding model
adding interventions and the AC click
prior together makes this a
this test error much lower
and we can observe it for for means as
well
I'm not going a little bit into details
on uh on this last experiment and on how
the acyclic prior acts on the structure
of the graph
so I perform I perform an experiment on
uh on a new data set which is I mean
calling in the new data set it may be
too much is that I call it a two means
data set in which you have the input
point is formed of of two different
images and the label only depends on the
second image
on the first image story
so the idea here is
is the structure of the model the
cyclicity prior and things like that
able to recognize that the second half
of the image is actually meaningless in
uh in performing in learning the
in performing classification
how does training behave in general like
for example we have this uh input input
node output node and only the nodes are
fully connected and the model
converge to a
to a hierarchical structure which is the
one that we know performs the best on on
classification tasks
well here is a is an example of a
Training Method
run so at c0 which is the beginning of
training
we have this model here so s0
corresponds to the to the seven so to
the first image as one corresponds to
the seven column image again we have the
label Y and all the latent variables x0
X1 X2
and the model is fully connected so the
agency Matrix
is is full of ones there are no zeros we
have self loops and things like that
the model for a couple of epochs until
and what we know immediately is that for
example the the model immediately
understands that the four is not needed
to perform classification so it doesn't
uh so every outgoing node from the from
the second input cluster is removed
and something we didn't understand is
that this is this cluster is the one
related to the output
so we have a
we have a linear map from s0 to Y
directly
which is this part here
but we know that actually a linear map
is not the best map for
performing classification of means so we
we need some hierarchy we need some
depth to to improve the results and as
you can see this line here is the is the
accuracy
which up to this point so up to C2 is
similar to um so it's 91 which is
slightly slightly better than linear
classification
but once you go on with the training
the model understands that it needs some
hierarchy to better fit the data
so you you see that this Arrow starts
getting stronger and stronger over time
until it it understands that the linear
map is not actually really needed and it
removes it
so the model you converge with is a
model that starts from a zero goes to a
hidden node and then goes to the
to the label with a very weak linear map
which actually gets removed if you if
you set a threshold of uh if seller
threshold of for example 0.1 0.2 at some
point the linear map gets forgotten and
everything you end up with is with a is
with a hierarchical network
that is that uh so it has learned the
correct structure to to perform
classification tasks which is hierarchy
and it has also learned that the second
image didn't play any role in defining
the the test accuracy and this is all
this is all performed also all those
jobs are simply performed by perform by
one free energy minimization process so
you initialize the model you define the
free energy you define the priors so the
the sparse and the C click prior
you run the the energy minimization and
you converge to hierarchical to a
hierarchical model which is well able to
perform classification on minced
and then if you then perform some fine
tuning you reach very competitive
results as you do in feed forward
networks with the feedback propagation
but I think that's not the interesting
bit the interesting bit is that you like
all this process this process all
together of intervention and the
acyclicity
allows you to take a fully connected
Network
and converge to a hierarchical one that
is that is able to perform
classification with good results
and yeah
that's basically it I'm now oh yeah wow
I've talked a lot and I'm uh this is the
conclusion of the talk which is a I'm
basically doing a small summary and I
think the the important takeaway if I
have to give you in one sentence of this
paper is that predictive coding is a
belief updating method that is able to
perform end-to-end cousin learning so
he's able to perform interventions to
learn a structure from data and and then
perform interventions and
counterfactuals
so causal inference in other and
efficiently model interventions by
simply setting the prediction error to
zero so it's a it's a very easy
technique to perform interventions and
you simply you only have to touch one
neuron you don't have to act on the
structure of the graph
you can you can use it to perform to to
create structure causal models that are
biologically plausible
it is able to learn the structure for uh
from data as I said maybe a lot of times
already and
and a couple of sentences about future
works is that
something that would be nice to do is to
improve the performance of the model we
we have defined because I think it
performs reasonably well on a lot of
tasks so it performs reasonably well on
structural learning on for me
intervention and counterfactuals but
actually if you look at state of the art
model there's always like a very
specific method that performs better in
the single task
so it would be interesting to see if we
can reach those level of performance in
uh in specific tasks by by adding some
tricks or some
or some new optimization methods and to
generalize it to to dynamical systems
which are actually much more interesting
the static systems so such as dynamical
causal models and or other techniques
that allow you to allow you to perform
causal inference in systems that move so
an action taken in a specific time step
influences another node in a later time
step which is a basically grandeur
causality
yeah that's it and uh
thank you very much
thank you awesome and very comprehensive
presentation that was really think
you're muted
sorry muted on Zoom but yes thanks for
the awesome and very comprehensive
presentation there was really a lot
there and there was also a lot of great
questions in the live chat so maybe to
warm into the questions how did you come
to study this topic were you study in
causality and found predictive coding to
be useful or vice versa or how did you
come at this intersection
I actually have to say that the first
person that came out with this idea was
uh was Baron
so so like like I think a year and a
half ago even more he brought like a
page with this idea and then he got
forgotten and no one picked it up and uh
and last summer I started getting
curious about causality and the
um I I read for example The Book of Life
as I listened to podcasts I know the
standard way in which you get interested
in a topic
and and I remember this this idea from
Baron and proposed it to him and uh and
I was like why don't we expand it and uh
and actually make it a paper so I I
involved some people to help me with
experiments and uh and this is the final
result at the end
awesome cool yeah
um
a lot to say I'm just gonna go to the
live chat first and address a bunch of
different questions and if anybody else
wants to add me I'm gonna turn the light
on first because I'm I think I'm getting
in the dark more and more yes
who said active inference can't solve a
dark room issue
oh yes here we are
so would you say the light switch caused
it to be lighter
yeah
I think so
no issues here
um okay ml Dawn wrote
since in predictive coding all
distributions are usually gaussian the
bottom up messages are Precision
weighted prediction errors where
Precision is the inverse of the gaussian
covariance what if non-gaussian
distributions are used
is a
basically the general method stays the
different the main difference is that
you you don't have prediction errors
which as was correctly pointed out is
the basically the derivative of the
virtual free energy if you have gaussian
assumptions
yeah you even have that single quantity
to set to zero and you probably will
have to act on the structure of the
graph
to perform interventions
and also you uh and colleagues had a
paper in 2022 predictive coding Beyond
gaussian distributions that that looked
at some of these issues right
yes yes exactly so that paper was a
little bit
the idea behind that paper is uh
and we model Transformers that's the
biggest motivation using pretty
difficulting and the answer is uh is not
because the the attention mechanism has
a soft Max at the end and soft Max calls
to uh
like not to gaussian distribution but to
yeah to soft Max distribution the I
don't get the name now but yes
and uh so yes that's a generalization
it's a little bit tricky to call it once
you remove the Gaston assumption is a
little bit still tricky to call it
creative coding
so he's a
so for example like talking to uh to car
Freestone either he like creative coding
is only if you if you have only Gauss
and gaussian assumptions
but yes that's more a philosophical
debate than uh
interesting and another I think topic
that that's definitely of of great
interest is similarities and differences
between the attention apparatus in
Transformers and the way that attention
is described from a neurocognitive
perspective and from a predictive
processing Precision waiting angle what
do you think about that
well the idea is that um
yeah I think about it is that in from a
pretty processing and and also
operational inference perspective
attention can be seen as a as a kind of
structural learning problem there's I
think there's a recent paper from uh
from Chris Buckley's group that shows
that
there should be there should be a
reprint on archive in which basically
they showed that the attention mechanism
is simply learning the the Precision on
the on the weight parameters specific to
other data point so this Precision is
not a it's not a it's not a parameter
that is in the structure of the model so
it's not a model specific parameter it
is a fast changing parameter like the
value nodes that gets updated while
minimizing the variation of free energy
and once they once you've minimized it
and compute it then you throw it away
and for the next data point you have to
recompute it from scratch
so yes I think the the analogy
computation wise is uh the attention
mechanism can be seen as a kind of
structure learning but a structure
learning that is data point specific and
not model specific
and I think if we want to generalize a
little bit and go from
from the attention mechanism in
Transformers the attention mechanism
cognitive science
I feel they're probably two different to
like to draw similarities and uh
I think the structural learning analogy
and the how important one Connection in
is with respect to another one probably
does the job much better
cool gray answer okay
ml Don asks in counterfactuals what is
the difference between hidden variables
X and unobserved variables U
the difference is that you can
I think the main one is that you cannot
observe the the use
you can use them because you can you can
compute them and fix them but you cannot
the idea is that you have no control
over them so they use the use should be
seen as a environment specific variables
that they are there they they influence
your process okay because the for
example when you go back in time the
environment is different so the idea is
for example if you
like going back to the to the example
before of the
of the expected income of a person with
a specific intelligence of Education uh
uh education degree
the idea is that if I want to to see how
much I will learn today with uh with a
with I don't know with a master degree
is different with respect to how much I
would earn
20 years ago with a master degree is
different for example here in Italy with
respect to other countries and all those
variables that are not under your
control you cannot model them using your
vision Network
but they are there okay so you you
cannot ignore them when you when you
want to draw conclusions so he's yeah
it's basically everything that you
cannot control
you can infer them so you can you can
perform a counter counterfactual
inference back in time and say oh 20
years ago I would have earned this much
if I
if I was this intelligent that this
degree on average of course
and but it's not that I can change the
government policies towards jobs or the
or things like that
it's a deeper counterfactual
yes exactly so yeah those are the use
awesome all right
have you implemented generalized
coordinates in predictive coding
no
I've no I've never done it I've uh
yeah I've studied it but I've uh I've
never implemented it I know they tend to
be unstable and uh
and it's very hard to make them stable I
think that's the that's the takeaway
that I got from talking to people that
have implemented them
but but yeah yeah I'm aware of some
papers that came out actually recently
about about them that that tested on
some British load encoder style actually
I think still from Baron there's a
there's a paper out there that came out
last summer but but no I've never played
them with them myself
cool romper
does adding more levels in the hierarchy
reduce the distraction problem of
predicting input
adding more level in uh
in which sense because the destruction
problem is given by Cycles so basically
you provide an image
and the fact that you have uh
so patches going out of the image going
in the neurons and then other edges
going back
this basically creates the fact that you
have a the error of that those basically
these in-going adjust to the pixels of
the image they create some prediction
errors so you have some prediction
errors that get spread inside the model
and that's yeah and this problem I think
is general of cycles and it's probably
not related to hierarchy in general
to the pixels
if you don't have incoming edges you
have no
uh no destruction problem anymore
cool and and the specification of the
acyclic network through the trace
operator
that's a very interesting technique and
when was that brought into play
uh as far as I know I think he came out
with the paper I I cited in 2018
I I don't know at least in the causal
inference literature I'm I'm not aware
of any previous methods I would say no
because that I mean that's the highly
cited paper so I would say they came out
with that idea
wow yeah that's that's quite nice that
you can do gradient descent and learn
the structure I think that's a
that's a very powerful technique yeah
sometimes it's like when you look at
when different
um features of Bayesian inference and
causal inference became available
it's really remarkable like why why
hasn't this been done under a Bayesian
causal modeling framework it's like
because there's only been like five to
25 years of this happening
and so that's very very short and also
it's relatively technical so there's
relatively few research groups engaging
in it and um it's just
really cool what it's enabling
no yes yes exactly I mean that's also I
think the exciting part of this field a
little bit that is uh I mean there are
definitely breakthroughs out there that
still have to be discovered and probably
like because for example like for as
much as a breakthrough that paper was
they found uh
like they simply found out the right
prior for acyclic structures
okay is a
yeah I mean I I don't know exactly but
it may be an idea that you have in one
afternoon I don't know about the story
of the how the others came up with that
but could potentially be that they
they're there at the Whiteboard you're
like oh that actually works that's a
huge breakthrough and I simply yeah
defined the prior
and also a lot of these breakthroughs
they they don't just stack it's not like
a uh uh a tower of blocks they they
layer and they compose so then something
will be generalized to um generalized
coordinates or generalize synchrony or
arbitrarily large graphs or
um Sensor Fusion with multimodal inputs
and it's like those all blend in really
satisfying and effective ways so so even
little things that again someone can
just come up with in a moment
um can really have impact
um okay ml Dawn says thanks a lot for
asking my questions and thanks a million
to Tomaso for the inspiring presentation
so nice oh thank you very much and then
Bert asks
how would language models using
predictive coding differ from those
using Transformers
um
okay I think that actually if I would
have to build today a language model
using predictive coding I will still use
the Transformers
so the idea is that for example if you
have a
let's say this hierarchical graphical
model of this or these hierarchical
Bayesian Network
I've defined in the in the very first
slides one Arrow to encode a function
which is the linear map
okay so one hour was simply the
multiplication of a of the vector
encoded in the latent variables times
the this weight Matrix that you can then
make non-linear and things like that but
that can be actually something much more
complex the the function included in the
arrow can be a convolution can be an
attention mechanism
so so actually how I would do it I will
still use the I mean which is actually
the way we did it in uh in in the Oxford
Group last year is that we we had
exactly the structure every arrow is a
Transformer now so one is the attention
mechanism and the the next one is the
feed forward Network as Transformers
and basically the only difference that
you have is that those variables you
want to compute the posterior and you
make those posteriors Independence
independent via VIA mean field
approximation so basically you follow
all the steps that allow you to to
converge to the very to the variation
free energy of creative coding but the
the way the way you compute predictions
and the way you send signals back
is uh is done via Transformer
so I will still use Transformers in
general I mean they work so well that I
I don't think that we can be arrogant
and say oh no I'm gonna do it better via
a purely predictive coding way
structures
but will still approximate Transformers
anyway
sorry you said structure learning would
approximate the Transformer approach
yes the structure learning I mentioned
earlier in uh when when someone uh asks
the similarities between creative coding
and the attention mechanism
very yeah very interesting
um
one thing I am wondering from Amazon I
could not see the concept of depth in
the predictive coding networks you
mentioned most likely I missed it the
definition provided for predictive
coding involved the concept of depth
what did you mean by depth
no yes it's true it's uh because the
standard definition as I said multiple
times is a is hierarchical you have
predictions go in One Direction some
prediction error going the opposite
direction
basically what uh what we did in in this
paper and also in the last one in uh
which is called The Learning on
arbitrary graph topologies we have
relative coding is that we can consider
depth uh like as a
as independent uh
basically pair of latent variable latent
variable and arrow
and you have predictions go in that
direction and prediction Arrow going
with the other but then you can compose
these in how many um a lot of ways so
you can you can so basically this
composition doesn't have to be
hierarchical in the end
can have Cycles so then you you can for
example plug in another uh another
latent variable to the first one and
then connect the others to and you can
have a structure is that is as entangled
as you want
so for example in the in the other paper
we train the
uh a Network that has the shape of a
brain structure so we have a lot of
brain regions that are sparsely
connected inside and it's partially
connected among each other
and and there's there's nothing
hierarchical there at the end but you
can still train it by minimizing
operational free energy and by
minimizing the the total prediction
error of the network
so you could have
for a given Motif in a entangled graph
you might see three successive layers
that when you looked at them alone you'd
say oh that's a three-story building
that's a three layer model that says
adaptive three but then when you take a
bigger picture there isn't like an
explicit top or an explicit bottom to
that Network
yes exactly and this is basically given
by the by the fact that every operation
in predictive Korean networks is uh is
strictly local
so so basically every message passing
every prediction and every prediction
error that you send you only send it to
the very nearby neurons okay and whether
the global structure is actually
hierarchical or not the the single
message passing doesn't even see that
I guess that's sort of
the hope for learning new model
architectures is the space of what is
designed top down is very small and a
lot of models in use today albeit super
effective models
um although you could ask effective per
unit of compute or not that's a second
level question but a lot of effective
models today do not have some of these
properties of predictive coding networks
like their capacity
um to to use only local computations
which gives biological realism
um or just spatio-temporal realism but
also May provide a lot of advantages in
like Federated compute or distributed
computing settings
no yes exactly I completely agree
because I think the idea in general is
that and I don't know if that's going to
be an advantage so I think it's very
promising exactly for the reasons you
said
and uh and the reason is that today's
model string with back propagation you
can basically uh summarize them as a as
a as a monitoring back propagation is a
function because basically you have a
map from input to output and back
propagation basically spreads uh
information back from its computational
graph so every neural network neural
network model used today
is a function while predictive coding
and another liberative coding like the
old class of functions that the class of
methods that that train in using local
computations and actually work by
minimizing a global energy function the
they're not limited to model functions
from input to Output they actually model
something that that kind of resembles
physical systems so you have a physical
system you fix some values to to
whatever input you have and you let the
system converge and then you read some
other value of uh neurons or variables
that are supposed to be output but this
physical system doesn't have to be a fit
forward map doesn't have to be a
function that has a an input space and
an output space and that's it
so the class of models that you can
learn is uh so basically you can see
like feed forward models and functions
and then a much bigger class which is
that of physical systems whether there's
something interesting out here I don't
know yet because the functions are
working extremely well we are seeing
those days with back propagation is a
they work crazy well but
so yeah I don't know if there's anything
interesting in the big part but the big
part is is quite big okay there are
there are a lot of models that you
cannot bring back propagation and you
can train with creative coding
or a bathroom propagation or other
methods
that is super interesting certainly
biological systems physical systems
solve all kinds of interesting problems
um
but there's still no free lunch
in ant species that does really well in
this environment might not do very well
in another environment and so um out
there in the in the Hinterlands there
might be some really unique special
algorithms that are not well described
by being a function
yet still uh provide like a procedural
way to to implement heuristics
which might be extremely extremely
effective
no yes yes exactly and uh yeah anything
this has been most of my
focus of research during my PhD for
example
like finding this application that is
like out here and not inside the the
functions
cool well
where does this work go from here like
what directions are you excited about
and how do you see people in the active
inference ecosystem getting involved in
this type of work
I think a very probably the most
promising Direction which is a
uh she's something maybe I would like to
to explore a little bit is to as I said
there really is to go behind statical
models so everything I've showed I've
shown so far is uh is about static data
so the the data don't change over time
there's no time inside the definition of
creative coding as it is as I presented
it here
however you can for example generalize
creative coding to to work with temporal
data using generalized coordinates as
you mentioned earlier uh by by
presenting it as a as a common Kalman
filter generative model
and and that's where for example the the
causal inference Direction could be very
useful because yeah that model uh at
that point maybe you can be able to
model greater causality and uh and more
complex and and useful uh
dynamical cause of models basically
because in general the the do calculus
and the Interventional and
counterfactual uh branch of science is
mostly developed on on small models
so it's a
like you don't do interventions on
gigantic models in general so if you if
you look at Medical Data they they use
relatively small Vision Networks and but
of course if you want to have a
dynamical causal model that models uh a
specific environment or a specific
reality you have a lot of neurons inside
you have a lot of latent variables they
change over time and an intervention at
some more at some moment creates an
effect in a different time step so maybe
in the next time step in 10 different
time steps later and I think that would
be very interesting to develop like a
biologically plausible way of passing
information
that is also able to model
Grandeur causality basically
hmm
where do you see action in these models
where do I see action
I didn't think of that
I think as the actions in those models
maybe in the same way as I as you see in
other models because
creative coding is basically a model of
perception
so so an action is you can see there's a
consequence of what you are experiencing
so by changing the way your your
experiencing something then you can
compute maybe you can simply perform a
smarter action now that you have more
information
but
but yeah I don't think action is very
easy like yeah I don't see any explicit
consequence of actions besides the fact
that this can allow you to basically
maybe do you
simply draw better conclusions to them
perform actions in the future
I'll add on to that a few ways that
people have uh talked about predictive
coding and action uh first off internal
action or covert action is attention so
we can think about perception as an
internal action that's one approach
another approach pretty micro is the
outputs of a given node we can
understand that node as a particular
thing with its own sensory cognitive and
action States and so in that sense the
the output of a node and then lastly
which we explored a little bit in live
stream 43 on the theoretical review on
predictive coding we're reading all the
way through and it was all about
perception all about perception and then
it was like section 5.3
if you have expectations about action
then action is just another variable in
this architecture and that's really
aligned with inactive inference where
instead of having like a reward or
utility function that we maximize we
select action based upon it being the
likeliest course of action the path of
least action that's Bayesian mechanics
and so it's actually very natural to
bring in an action variable and utilize
it essentially as it as if it were a
prediction about something else
extra receptively in the world because
we're also expecting action
no yes yes exactly
no I like the way of defining actions a
lot actually and uh and I still think it
has been like for example there are not
so many papers that apply this method I
think there are a couple from uh from
Alexander or robria does something
similar but in practice like outside of
the pure active inference like applying
predictive coding and actions to to
solve practical problems hasn't been uh
explored a lot
oh well thank you for this excellent
presentation and discussion is there
anything else that you want to um say or
or Point people towards
uh no just a big thank you for inviting
me and uh
it was really fun and I hope to come
back at some point for for some Future
Works
cool
anytime anytime thank you Thomas so
thank you Daniel see you bye bye